so the time we have been waiting for is
here how many people love
plumba how many people have been blessed
and inspired like I have we love you
Prof as the empowerment Nation we are
honored to know you we are honored to
connect to you you are a blessing you
are a generational blessing I wanted to
say you are a blessing to this
generation but you are a generational
blessing we look up to you you are a
leader that has been a pay Setter and a
trailblazer
and we thank God for your life put your
hands together as I bring to this uh uh
Pulpit Professor
[Music]
plumba thank you very much if you may
resume your seats
let me say how glad I
am to be present with
you at this time of worship this
evening on this Monday the 19th day of
June the year
2023 I want to share with you a message
but before I do so I invite
Karina to read a
poem which I consider to be one of the
most powerful poems ever written by man
is a short poem let I read
it
fear it is said that before entering the
sea a river trembles with fear she looks
back at the path she has traveled from
the peaks of the mountains the long
winding Rod Crossing forests and
Villages and in front of her she sees an
ocean so vast that to enter there seems
nothing more than to disappear forever
but there is no other way the river
cannot go back
nobody can go back to go back is
impossible in existence the river needs
to take the risk of entering the ocean
because only then will fear
disappear because that's where the river
will know it's not about disappearing
into the ocean but of becoming the
[Music]
ocean thank you very much
you
know when we say of God that is from
Everlasting to
Everlasting we mean exactly
that and those of you who are
believers will find several scriptures
in the
Bible that talk about
faith that talk
about moments of
doubt and many of them are known to
you one of
them that I
love that talks about
faith is a conversation between
Christ and
Phillip when he asks of
Christ we have seen you
Now show us the
father and Christ tells him but Phillip
I've been with you all this
while but you still ask of the
Father the father is in me and I am in
the father for he who has seen me has
seen the father you are seen the river
seen the ocean
the other one that I
love comes to all of us in moments of
doubt it is a
conversation involving Phillip and
Nathaniel and
Nathaniel I involved in a conversation
he said there is a man he must be one of
whom the prophets talked about
about whom Moses
talked he comes from
Nazareth then he says Nathaniel but what
good come can come out of
Nazareth many of us find ourselves in
that
space when our background is used
against
us and we doubt
ourselves and yet there is a s in which
doubt is the mother of
faith I
remember when you read the Bible it
tells
us that on the day that Christ himself
was
baptized the Lord appeared as he was
being
baptized and told John the
Baptist this is my my son in whom I am
pleased but yet this very John the
Baptist when he is in
prison he is in
doubt and he sends two of his dis
disciples to go to Christ and to ask of
Christ are you the one or we should wait
for another and Christ does not say that
I am the one he says go and tell
John the lame
walk the blind see the lepers are clean
are
cleansed and the gospel is being
preached to the poor I often wonder to
myself how John must have felt because
he's then executed
and that is what brings me to what I
want to talk about
today
character and
choices cuz the world is about choices
making
choices and when you look at the Bible
it has always been about what choice do
you
make you who are believers will be
familiar with that famous
contest between Elijah and the prophets
of
B the
450 of
them and the contest is organized at
Mount
carel and the prophets of Bal pray unto
their God and they are mocked by
Elijah but before that Elijah tells the
is Israelites Choose You
Now if God is God worship him if Bal is
God worship
Him and many times in our lives we are
called upon to make
choices difficult
choices and we know the story of how it
all ends up the prophets of B pray unto
their God and nothing happened and
Elijah invokes the name of the true
God and fire comes down and the
sacrifice is
consumed is about
choices and is about
character the other
major choice is to be found in the book
of The Prophet
Joshua and you'll
remember when when Joshua has moved the
Israelites and they are facing the
Jordan the people are confused as they
are want to be
confused and he tells
them choose you
now whom You Shall
Serve will you
serve the gods of our ancestors that
they prayed to before they cross the
river or you will serve the god of the
amorites in whose Land We dwell as for
me and my house I Shall Serve the Lord
it is a choice that must be made but is
a choice that must be defined by one's
character because as I talk to you now
we live in difficult and perilous times
the times about
which the Bible talks about the times
about which the prophets have spoken
throughout the ages these are those
times these are the times that when Paul
is writing his second letter to Timothy
at chapter 3 talks of those times in the
end days there shall be a form of
Christianity where people shall be
lovers of themselves and they shall have
a form of Christianity which does not
honor God and he proceed to say just as
Janice and jambus troubled Moses in the
desert so shall they do but they shall
not succeed these are those times these
are those times that are talked about in
Matthews
24:24 that in this end days that there
shall arise many christs and they shall
work wonders and that if it were
possible they would deceive even the
very elect these are those
times these are those times of which in
Paul's letter to Timothy in the Book of
Romans he says that they shall be haters
of God at Roman 130 shall they shall be
haters of God and they shall be inventor
of new sins they will have committed all
sins and they'll invent new ones these
are those
times and these are the times therefore
when we must ask ourselves who are
we
because it is very easy to be a
Christian when all is
good it is very easy to say your
Hallelujah when there is no advice
unities it is very easy to say that on
the 19th day of the month of June the
year
2023 I was born again the Lord appeared
unto me when you are in the comfort of
Nairobi it's very easy to say so but
it's not so very easy to say so when you
have no food on your table it is not
easy to say so when you do not know now
you shall
survive it is not
easy true Christianity is only
discovered when you are faced with
adversity when you have your own little
Golgotha when you have to make a
choice and that is
why sometimes when I talk about
character I find great wisdom in the
Book of Daniel
and when you read the book of Daniel in
chapter one it tells us that in the
third year of the reign of Joakim the
king of Judah the kingdom was captured
by nebuch
cadz and he took the Israelites as
captives and King
Nebuchadnezzar then as the chief of the
unics as spenner
to go into the land of Judah and select
from within their ranks young men who
are knowledgeable in the Arts and in the
sciences and in everything and to bring
them that they may come into the kingdom
into the temple into the Palace of
nebuchad that they may be trained that
they may serve
nebuchad and we are told that he went
into Judah and picked four young men one
was called
Daniel the other one was called
hananiah the other one was called mishel
the other one was called aeria and King
Nebuchadnezzar changed their names unto
Daniel he became Belta shaza unto hanani
became Shadrach unto M he became
Abednego and we know Shadrach he became
mesach and unto aaria he became
Abednego many of us who read the Bible
do not remember the
names we only remember Shadrach mesach
and
Abednego and they came to be in the
palace and Ash
penas was in instructed by
Nebuchadnezzar to feed the young men
with
wine with meat which you all of us would
love meat from the palace wine from the
palace but Daniel said I am asking you I
do not want to eat of the meat of the
palace and of the wine of the palace
because they have been sacrificed to
idols and ashena
said if you do
that it shall not be good for me and
Daniel said give us a trial for only 10
days that you may see how we are and the
Bible says after 10
days they looked better than everybody
else they looked better than every
everybody
else and after several years they were
brought before
Nebuchadnezzar and we are told that they
were 10 times better than everybody else
in their wisdom in their science in
their arts in their everything
Daniel the dreamer the interpretor of
the dreams Shadrach and Abednego and
they were revered throughout Babylon
but then we are told as it is always in
humanity when you are doing well you
have no shortage of
enemies there are those who want to
bring you down there are those who want
to malign you there are those who want
to destroy you you remember even in the
case of Christ the very same people who
sang hosana in the highest are the very
same who say crucify him that is like
they sing hosana in the highest when
they think you are going nowhere when
you are going somewhere they say crucify
him crucify him the history of the world
is that when they are given a choice
between Christ and Barabas the world
will always say release
Barabas release Barabas that is the
nature of
humanity so Shadrach mesak and Abednego
have demonstrated to nebuch
cadz that they have a gifting that they
have an anointing that they are beloved
of God that they are possessed of wisdom
that we have talked
about but then they have no shortage of
enemies and enemies are manufacturers of
Lies throughout the ages they
manufacture lies they create lies they
they invent lies they malign you they
dehumanize you they humiliate you they
denigrate you and if you allow them to
do that then you collapse and they hold
parties about it and some of your worst
enemies are your closest friends in
quotes un quotes that is why we
sometimes says oh Lord save me for my
friends because my enemies I
know so it is with Shadrach mesak and a
bedo so somebody looks at
them and see Daniel doing very
well Shadrach doing very
well mesach doing very well AB bed Neo
doing very well and they are not happy
with that and they go to the king and
say oh King you are great king you must
be worshiped and they make an idol of
King
Nebuchadnezzar and King
Nebuchadnezzar gives the decree saying
that everybody shall worship that
image and of course they worship that
image and they have set a trap for
Shadrach mesach and
Abednego and Shadrach M and bedne
refused to Bow unto that
image and they are reported to nebuchad
NZ and Nebuchadnezzar summons them and
say I am told that you have refused to
worship my
image
why and they tell
Nebuchadnezzar we worship only one true
God and we shall not bow unto anybody
and the decree has said that anybody who
disobeys Nebuchadnezzar shall be thrown
into a furnace of
fire and this is the most beautiful
thing that I've ever loved they say if
you throw us into the
fire the god that we serve will rescue
us but even if he does
not CU many of us only worship God when
he does that which we desire but these
three young men say even if he does
not even if he does not we shall
continue to be faithful to
him and the Bible says that
Nebuchadnezzar then summoned some of the
widest chested men in
Babylon and and they tied the young men
and threw them into the furnace and the
Bible records that as they were throwing
them into the furnace they themselves
were consumed by the fire that is how
hot it was seven times heated
over and then a few minutes later
Nebuchadnezzar looks Into the Fire and
he sees the young man walking
majestically and he says but we threw in
three young men we see a fourth person
who is like the son of the
Gods you
know when I listen and read that
story he tells me about
character he tells me about
character because Shadrach mesak and
Abednego Niah mishel and aaria Daniel is
Belta shazah you change their names but
they don't object you can change my name
you can call me anything call me a fool
call me
anything but that does not change
me you can call me anything call me a
fool call me anything call me shadra
mesak but that is only
Sky because A Rose by Any Other Name is
but a rose
but when you want to change the things
that make sense that Define who I am who
I worship and what I do then I'm
prepared to give my life that is
character what are you prepared to die
for this is the question you know it
would have been very easy for Shadrach
mesak and
Abednego to say oh King you are Mighty
we shall worship you we shall with our
mouths worship you but in our hearts we
shall believe in God no God says that if
you are lukewarm he shall spew you out
it is either him or nobody
else I do not know how many of you have
watched the film 10
commandments there are many Ten
Commandments but there is one ten
commandment
which was in
1956 that Ten Commandment has Charon hon
acting as Moses and UL Brina as
rameses and I always remember these
words when Charon hon as Moses has gone
into the mountain of the Lord and is up
there and he is receiving the Ten
Commandments and when he is receiving
the Ten Commandments and he tells God
you are from Everlasting to Everlasting
and he says pick me not pick my brother
Aaron because I am slow of speech and
the Lord tells him it is me who is the
maker of speeches I shall make you a god
unto Aaron and whatever you do Aaron you
ask of Aaron he shall do unto you and he
gives him the Ten Commandments and when
is coming up down from the mountain of
the Lord below there is already a
Rebellion death and Janice and jambus
have told the entire crowd of Israel how
can a man survive for 40 days and 40
nights let us make unto ourselves a God
let us enjoy ourselves and they do and
as Moses walks down in that
dramatization he meets Joshua who is
acted by John Derek and Joshua tells him
there is rebellion there is an attack on
the people and Moses says no that is the
song of joy and dance and rry the people
have rebelled against God and when he
comes down and he hold the two tablets
of the Ten Commandments naan appears
unto him and the sons of Kor and says
you have made unto yourself laws that
you may become a king over us we are
free and Moses says there is no Freedom
outside of the law
that is
character there is no Freedom outside of
the
law and the Book of Daniel affirms to us
that when you be a person of character
you must be a person who is prepared to
face all adversity and to be prepared to
die for something throughout the Bible
they have always been men and women of
character who have been prepared to die
for something because ultimately what
you are prepared to die for is what
defines how you
live you
know when I
read the acts of the
Apostle there is a man known as
Simon Simon the
Sorcerer or Simon Magus you'll meet him
in the Acts of the
Apostles he sees Peter performing
miracle Les and he tells Peter you know
he was a levitator he could levitate it
could float in the air to demonstrate
how great he was and on that day Peter
prays and he stops him in the air I
don't know whether you have read The
Acts of the Apostles where Simon Magus
is stopped midia when he's
levitating and then he comes to Peter
and say this thing that you have I want
to buy it there are people will want to
buy bu that which is in you because they
believe that you can be bought but the
question is do you have character that
will tell them I have no
value you cannot buy me do you have the
moral Courage the moral strength are you
capable of being enticed by Earthly
things because today we have no shortage
of people who are prepared to buy you
for anything are you prepared to
sacrifice are you prepared to sacri to
sell your soul for 30 pieces of silver
are you prepared to surrender you are
all remember all this has been done you
remember that story when Christ himself
is taken by Satan and taken to the
mountain and is shown all the kingdoms
present and kingdoms yet to come and he
tells him bow before me and all these
shall be yours
but can you do it of your own will no
you are
weak you are made of clay you are weak
you cannot resist it when you are
properly tempted you will fall history
has shown the fall of men because they
were weak because they avoided the right
thing tell me if you read the book in
The Genesis they were weak Adam was weak
Eve was weak Abraham was weak that is
when he is confronted he was weak and
selfish he say Sarah is my sister he was
weak Samson was weak Moses was weak
people are weak in the Bible when they
don't go to God they are weak everybody
is weak strength only comes when you
believe in a power that is outside of
you and that is what character is all
about that is why when Christ is told
you are good man he says who is
good but only God who is
good when you are weak in the flesh that
is when you become an instrument for God
so the choice is yours because today as
I said we live in perilous
times when the word of God is
perverted you must have a Discerning
spirit
and that is why Paul says that when he
went and he met the Christians of Bera
he liked the Christians of Bera because
the Christians of the Bera when the word
had been preached unto them they went
back and looked at the word and said Is
it
true there is no shortage of men even
the by the Devil Himself can quote
scriptures he did on that day when God
assembled the sons of God and the son of
men and he came and the Lord asked him
where what are you doing he said I've
been loitering around the world and he
told God oh God told him that is's a man
who pretends to love you but he does not
you tempt him a little and if you tempt
him a little and if you take the thing
that he has then he will deny you and he
said you go unto job do all the evil
things against him but do not take his
life and the things started disappearing
one by one one by one one by one one by
one and the friends of job came to him
one by one one by one telling him oh job
why are you worshiping this God who
cares not for you why don't you turn
against him and his own very wife told
him job why are you continuing to
worship this God but he had
character he had character and he with
stod
the tsunamis
can you withstand the
tsunamis can you withstand the tsunamis
that we now face in this country and in
this
world when you live in a
world where the worth of a person is
measured by material
things if you are a lady we are asking
you which perfume are you
wearing is it
Donan and if you don't wear Donan we
don't think you are doing very
well which bag are you carrying is it
Louis
V and if you are not carrying Louis V we
don't think you are doing very well
which watch are you wearing is it radar
or
Rolex which car are you driving
these are the things that are testing
your
character can you withstand all those
tests or you will succumb cuz these are
the latterday BS these are the things
that have been made unto us that they
may test us and if you are man which
underwear you wearing
us which shoes are you wearing is it
Tommy Hill
figure these are the question which tie
are you wearing which car are you
driving is it a
V8 or a Range
Rover which gold are you going to sell
or pretend to sell that you may please
the other John says there is no shortage
of
temptation but yet you must be strong
enough to say like Alexander the Great
empty-handed I came and empty-handed I
shall leave vanity of vanity you must be
able to say with Solomon I've tried all
these Solomon of the Bible of whom we
say he was
wise he says in the book of
lamentation if it is women I had a
thousand of them 700 as my wives 300 as
my concubine
if it is clothes I had the most
beautiful clothes on Earth I had it all
but then Solomon the son of David says
it is all
vanity of
vanities
character
sometimes I imagine to
myself on that day of
judgment when the books are
opened and all of
us we Pretenders who are present in
these and many
assemblies who look p as if we are
Heavenly
baked on that
day when our sins known and unknown are
opened unto us
and they are counting them one by
one will you withstand the
test will
you you who are so P you who are giving
tithe on a daily
basis oh you
who you who could say the hour and the
minute when you are born
again you was a Bible sing Sunday and
Saturday attending church on a daily
basis but you who are alone was
Jezebel will you withstand the test
because character is not about what you
do to please
us character is about what you do
because it is good to be good and
because it is divinely ordained
you can cheat US most of the
time but God says he's omnipresent and
omniscient Every Act every thought he
says he says I number the hair on your
head when you are dealing with such a
being you must be very careful extra
careful cuz he knows you are very act
you are very thought before you think he
knows and that is why we have all sinned
and fallen short of the glory of God and
is only by his
grace but we must make effort in fact
sometimes I dare think at the risk of
being heretical that on the day of
judgment we shall be made to pass on the
basis of our effort there is a column I
think in the marking scheme of Heaven
which is called
effort what effort did you make
genuinely to do
good in this
world and that is why I understand
Shadrach mesak and Abed go say the
result is not in our hands we shall do
that which is good and right but we are
not responsible for the result that is
why they say we will worship the true
God but it matters not if he does not
rescue us he does not cease to be
God you and
me we perennial Sinners we evildoers you
and
me who are in the business of thinking
that a church and God is running a
lottery and a casino where we buy the
ticket and we win the jackpot and if we
don't win the jackpot then we blame God
we are
doomed there is no Casino in heaven
there is no lottery ticket salvation is
not a lottery ticket no if you think is
a lottery ticket that guarantees that
you shall have a beautiful life that
when you become born again then you are
shifted into Shangri La or El Dorado the
land of gold no your life begins to be
painful when you accept to do the right
thing one of the most dangerous things
to be today in this country called Kenya
is to be a honest man and woman if you
are honest you are
endangered if you are truthful you are
endangered if you want to do good you
are
endangered we have become a land where
we canonize thieves and demonize Saints
this is the land in which we live you
have become a country where
virtue is vice and vice is virtue we
have become a country where we have
turned material things into God we
worship men and worship and we mock God
we go to church every Sunday and even to
most and we mock God we
site The Lord's
Prayer mocking God
weide the Creeds mocking
God God is
patient in Paul's letter to Romans
chapter 1 verse 28 says I shall abandon
them that they may do what it is that
they want to
do because they have become inventors
and innovators of new
sins that is who we are because we have
no character
so the most defining things throughout
the ages is character if you have
character you must show it and at
critical times even the weakest of men
in critical matters they have always
shown
character when Abraham left Ur of the
calans go to the unnown and behold he
end
Moses left the Palace of the Pharaohs
into an unkown land soured in the desert
for 40 years and he goes back to the
Pharaoh and does one of the most foolish
things empty-handed he says the Lord my
God says Let My People Go by
faith
Joshua
goes crossing the
Jordan and makes a chice when everybody
else is a coward he says as for me and
my house We Shall Serve the
Lord a bunch of
cowards if you
have the Disciples of Christ were a
bunch of
cowards all of
them cuz they thought like we always do
that Christ has come to to to build a
kingdom where they would be
ministers and that is how I understand
the sons of zebede when their mother
accompanies them how many of you have
accompanied our children to a government
office is the same thing they
accompanied their sons to Christ and
said we want one to be on your left side
and the other one to be on your right
and Christ says as to who shall be on my
left and right it is not me to determine
by the
father but they shall
be they were disappointed because they
thought that this man would come and
change their world and many of us who
worship God we come to work we come to
this Sanctuary expecting a miracle that
if the Reverend my good sister Natasha
prays to you tomorrow the doors of all
jobs in the world will open unto you no
that is for God to
determine not
her we are instruments of God and God
has his own time of choosing yet we say
oh it did not happen and therefore God
does not
function yet this bunch of cowards who
after Christ has been crucified they go
out and they said there came a man there
was a man who came here and this man
came and he was crucified and everybody
goes back to their fishing Peter goes
back to his fishing everybody goes and
one day on the journey to him house
something
happens this semil literates this
cowards
suddenly become totally different and on
the day of the Pentecost something
happens to them and people are saying
what has happened to them it is in the
morning they are drunk and Peter says
but how can we be drunk in the hours
before noon because alcohol was consumed
in the
afternoon they are speaking in tongues
and the world was never the same
again 2,000 years that message whether
you doubt it or not it is alive and
well and there's no shortage of doubt
that that message is Alive and Well I
remember listening to one of the most
classic sermons ever delivered by Man
Billy Graham in 1971 in Chicago in the
United States of America we ask who is
this Jesus Christ and you say this man
whom whether you like him or not whe
when you meet him you are never the same
again
and he says in that sermon that look at
the Young Rich man who comes to Christ
and Christ asks him do you want to join
to see the Kingdom of Heaven he says
have you obeyed all the laws of Moses
and he says I've done all that then he
says there is only one thing that I want
you to do go and sell all your things
and once you sold them follow me and the
young man goes dejected and Christ then
says how difficult shall it be for a
person to get into the Kingdom of Heaven
character choose you now which you what
you shall worship it is temporal
things all the Divine unclear things by
faith and this message has been preached
and will be preached for a long time and
you who are present here today I'm
asking you to wear the spirit of
Shadrach mesach and Abed let your name
be changed let them call you all they
want to call you but when it comes to
making a determination of what is good
and what is right tell them I shall do
that which is good and right because it
is good and right to do so and I shall
do so at the pain of death and let what
will be be God bless you because he's
from Everlasting to Everlasting
[Applause]
somebody say powerful powerful I just
want you to just reflect on that message
for 30 seconds and just tell God like
shedrach mishek and Abednego I want to
become a woman of character I want to
become a man of character that in season
and out of season I will serve God that
I will not do things the popular way I
will do things the proper way like
shedrach mishek and Abednego